<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vials of the wrath of God poured forth upon the seat of the man of sin, and upon all professors of the world, who denieth the light of Christ which he hath enlightned every one withal, and walk contrary to it, with it they are condemned : and a vvarning from the Lord to all who are walking headlong to destruction in the lusts of the flesh, and deceits of the world, that they may repent and turn to the Lord, lest the overflowing scourge sweep them all into the pit / by him who is called George Fox.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1975</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39551</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18429177</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18429177</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107633</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40314)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107633)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1632:64)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vials of the wrath of God poured forth upon the seat of the man of sin, and upon all professors of the world, who denieth the light of Christ which he hath enlightned every one withal, and walk contrary to it, with it they are condemned : and a vvarning from the Lord to all who are walking headlong to destruction in the lusts of the flesh, and deceits of the world, that they may repent and turn to the Lord, lest the overflowing scourge sweep them all into the pit / by him who is called George Fox.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and slightly faded, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>God --  Wrath.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107633:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>VIALS OF The Wrath of God, Poured forth Upon the ſeat of the MAN of SIN, And Upon all profeſſors of the WORLD, who denieth the light of Chriſt which he hath enlightned every one withal, and walk contrary to it; with it they are condemned.</p>
            <p>AND A VVARNING from the LORD to all who are walking headlong to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in the luſts of the fleſh, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of the world, that they may repent and turn to the Lord, leſt the overflowing ſcourge ſweep them all into the pit.</p>
            <p>By him who is called <hi>George Fox.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the black ſpread-Eagle at the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:107633:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107633:2"/>
            <head>The Worlds PROFESSION without Foundation. With Several precious Notes to Great men, and Rich men.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL profeſſion of the world is without ground, and the foundation; for the light is denied of the world, and hated: profeſſors, Prieſts and people, and all who hates the light, their deeds are evil, and they will not bring their works to the light, leſt the light ſhould reprove them, they know their deeds are evil, thou wilt not bring thy works, leſt the light ſhould reprove them: drunkard, thou knoweſt thy deeds are evil, thou wilt not bring thy works to the light, leſt the light ſhould reprove thee, there thou haſt learned thy condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is the light. Lyer thou knoweſt thou ſhouldſt not lye, there thou haſt learned thy condemnation, the light, and ſwearer and railer, thou knoweſt thou ſhouldſt not ſwear nor rail, the light within thee lets thee ſee thy deeds are evil, and it makes thee confeſs thy deeds are evil, there thou haſt learned thy condemnation, the light; Ye deviliſh mindes who are hatching miſchief, plotting together to do miſchief in Alehouſes and upon your beds, ſomething in your conſciences tells you, <hi>You ſhould not do ſo,</hi> there you have learned your condemnation, the light; ye curſed ſpeakers, envious ones, quarrellers, fighters, ſtoners, wrathful malicious ones, there is ſomething in your conſciences tells you, <hi>All this to be of the devil,</hi> there you have learned your condemnation, the light that Chriſt hath enlightned you withal, which lets you ſee your deeds are evil when you are ſitting in Alehouſes, drinking, carding, ſhovelboording, ſwearing by <hi>God,</hi> or your <hi>Soul,</hi> or your <hi>Faith,</hi> or curſing and provoking one another to wrath, fighting and abuſing one another, ſo you are them that defiles the fleſh, there is ſomething in your conſciences tells you, <hi>All this to be of the devil,</hi> there you have learned your condemnation, which is the light which lets you ſee all the works of darkneſs.</p>
            <p>Now therefore hearken to the light which may lead you up to God the Father of light, it lets you ſee, you ſhould not lye, not ſteal, not commit adultery, you ſhould not walk in unclean act ons, and all you that do, you know your deeds are evil by the light in your conſciences, which is your condemnation, the light in your conſciences which ſhould exerciſe it, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107633:3"/>all you wanton luſtful ones, ſporting your ſelves, who gather your ſelves together to ſpend your time in vanity, there is ſomething in your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences tolls you, <hi>All that to be fally, fooliſhneſs and madneſs: Laughter is mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> faith the prophet, and who is grown ſolid and civil, and denies ſuch practices that is counted madneſs with you, who live in folly, there is that in your conſciences lets you ſee your deeds to be evil, you have learned the condemnation the light, which when the book of all conſciences is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened you will all witneſs what I ſpeak. To that in your conſciences do I ſpeak, then the time will come that you will wiſh you had not been born into the world.</p>
            <p>Now you eaſeful ones are at eaſe, and you profeſſors Prieſts and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, have ſet you neſts ſo high as though none could reach you; and all you conceited ones, who reſt in your conceits; and you worldlings, who are drunk with the cares of this life; and you covetous ones, who devour one another, for the creature, for the earth, the time is coming when the poor deſpiſed ones ſhall ſit down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and a cry will be among all you, and an howling, a wiſhing you had never been born.</p>
            <p>Lyer, thou are for the lake that burns; unbelievers, you are for the lake; drunkards and ſcorners, you are for the lake that burns, and ſhall never inherit the kingdom of God who act ſuch things; drunkard, thou haſt caſt the Law of God behinde thy back; and you that minde earthly things, your end is deſtruction, whoſe God is your belly, who glories in your ſhame, who live <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the luſt, drunkenneſs, gluttony devouring the creation, a time will come that you will wiſh ye had never been born, for you have all known in your dayes, that your deeds have been evil, and that you have done contrary to the light in your conſciences, there is your condemnation, the light, for you wicke will be as the chaff which the winde driveth away, and all you proud will be as the ſtubble, the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</p>
            <p>This is to be ſcattered among the ignorant, ſimple and blinde people, led by the God of the world, and drunkenneſs, and luſt, that the witneſs may ariſe in them, againſt theſe ungodly deeds, that they may be left without excuſe, who have had a time, and a viſitation to call to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Now you have time prize it, you have light which Chriſt hath given you, to it I ſpeak, which lets you ſee all your dees to be evil, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, it will be your condemnation. To all manner of people I ſpeak, it will eternally witneſs me, and condemn you.</p>
            <p>Some are drunk with drink, ſitting together to invent miſchief, to ſhed blood, to deſtroy the innocent. Another company, Prieſts and people, are got together, drunk with rage and perſecution, as drunk as the other are, in rage and madneſs, plotting and inventing together againſt the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, to ſhed innocent blood, ſome you get into priſon: and you are worſe then common drunkards, for you ſtock, and cauſe the innocent to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107633:3"/>be impriſoned. Therefore awake all drunkards, and ſear God, and turn unto the Lord while ye have time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharaoh</hi> thou oppreſſor, <hi>pharaoh</hi> thou taskmaſter, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> thou proud one which lays heavy burthens upon the innocent and righteous ſeed, and opreſleth the juſt, plagues and woe is thy protion, as was <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s, who taxes, and oppreſſes, and cauſeth the juſt and righteous ſeed to labour under thee, who bindes with oathes, and compels to ſwear by that which is a declaration of Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> and, <hi>He that doth not abide in the doctrine of Christ, hath not God, but is of the devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O ye earthly minded men! give over oppreſſing the poor, exalt not your ſelves above your fellow-creatures; for ye are all of one mold and blood; you that ſet your neſts on high, joyne houſe to houſe, field to field till there be no place for the poor, woe is your portion. <hi>The earth is the Lords and the fulneſs thereof.</hi> And you that have not ſo much of the earth, give over your murmuring and reaſoning, fretting and grudging, for all your want is for the want of God: the righteous God is coming to give to every one of you according to your works: now the works of ye all muſt be tried, you that have appeared unto men beautiful outwardly, will be found in the generation of murtherers, and ye that have pretended to worſhip, your ſacrifice will be found to be <hi>Cains,</hi> which God hath no reſpect to.</p>
            <p>O ye high ones which ſpread your ſelves, appear fair, tall and ſtrong! you know not God, nor your ſelves to be oakes. O ye tall Cedars! ye know not your ſelves to be ſo, the Lord is ſent to look for fruit in his vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard among you, it is full of wilde Olives, and their wilde Grapes, that many are drunk with the juyce of the wilde Grapes; and ſo the vineyard is full of bryers and thornes, that the lambs and ſheep cannot paſs, but they are tangled among the bryers and the thornes; and the Land is as a wilderneſs; that part full of Serpents; and the earth is overgrown with with weeds and nettles, that there is no feeding for the lambs till the earth be dreſſed and overturned.</p>
            <p>Howle ye vinedreſſers! a day of howling is coming among you, who have been pretenders of the dreſſer of the vineyards, which is overgrown with weeds, and nettles, and thornes, and crooked wayes, the lambs and ſheep hath been ſcattered and devoured amongſt the bryers and the thornes, and no diſcerning you have had betwixt a lamb, a goat, a ſheep, a wolf. Now the Lord himſelf is gathering his lambs and his ſheep where they have been ſcattered this cloudy dark day, and ſome are torn, and ſome are trampled upon with the horſes of <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> but the Lord his hand againſt you, and his ſword drawn, the battel is begun, and the ſword drawn, which muſt not be put up till it hath made a ſeparation in hewing down, and the Lord himſelf will have the praiſe, and the honor and the renown, and all, who rules.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:107633:4"/>
O how beautiful hath thy Harlot been? O how full is the land of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanters? O how full is the land of Sorcerers &amp; witchcrafts! the myſtery of her hath deceived many through her whoredoms. Green was the graſs, &amp; freſh was the flowers, the bay-tree ſpread it ſelf, and the haw-thorn, but the time is coming of fading; the flower will fade, and the graſs will wither, and the whoredom and the inchanter muſt come to judgement; the Lord is riſen and riſeth as a ſwift witneſs againſt the inchanter, againſt the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers, againſt the whoremongers and the covetous. The glittering ſword is drawn to hew down you fruitleſs trees which cumber the ground, ye luſtful fleſhly ones, you have not ſeen your ſelves to be theſe trees which cumber the ground: ye heady high-minded ones, you have not ſeen your ſelves to be theſe trees which cumber the ground: ye who live in the fleſh, ye do not ſee your ſelves to be theſe trees which cumber the ground: ye ſcorners, ye lyers, ye diſſemblers, falſe hearts, ye do not ſee your ſelves to be theſe trees which cumber the ground: but the Lord is riſen againſt you; the earth ſtinks with the dead that is upon it, and the pollution of the polluted. The Lord is riſen with power, and ſending forth to bury the dead, and to raiſe up the dead: all who are immortal, this may ſee, may receive.</p>
            <p>Repent, for the day of the Lord is coming. Awake ye worldlings, hearken to that in your conſciences, which ſhews you ſin and evil, that will guide you unto God, loving it. Awake ye drunkards and luſtful ones, who follow pleaſures, conſider the wayes you walk in, for you who act ſuch things, muſt never inherit the kingdom of God; for you act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that in your conſciences, which will be your condemnation, pride, and ambition, ſelfiſhneſs, and ſelf-will, ſtands up; which the plagues of God are due unto: ſilence all fleſh, who lives in your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and deceit, thieving and ſtealing in the night, what the Saints ſpoke, making your ſelves drunk with it, and then ſells it to drunkards, and then are jovial, eating and drinking with drunkards. Howle ye drunkards, for ye ſhall want the ſtaffe of bread; a day of howling is coming upon you, lay aſide all deceitful merchandize.</p>
            <p>And all ye Star-gazers, who are gazing among the Stars, wondering after your imaginations, doing the works of darkneſs, in whom lodgeth the Spirit of witchcraft.</p>
            <p>Silence, and come down all ye that ride ſo high, that do beſtir ye as <hi>Jannes</hi> did, and <hi>Jambres,</hi> at the coming of the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Aegypt:</hi> through the fire and the ſea, ye cannot come.</p>
            <p>Silence all preſumptious talkers of God, who ſees him not, but are preſumptious boaſters, who live in envie, croſsneſs, and perverſneſs, and vain contention, which proceeds from corrupt mindes, who mindes the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107633:4"/>earth and earthly things, who are enemies to the croſs of Chriſt, who glories in your ſhame, whoſe end is deſtruction, whoſe belly is your God, who do not ſee God, are not come ſo far as <hi>Moſes;</hi> for <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw God face to face; and death reigns from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and all that ſees not God, death reigns in you. To that in your conſcience I ſpeak, which Chriſt hath enlightned you whithal, which calls you to repentance, which ſhews you your evil deeds, which will be your teacher owning and loving it, your condemnation hating it. Now you have time, prize it, this is the day of your viſitation.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Fox.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="warning">
            <head>A Warning from the LORD to all Hawkers and Hunters.</head>
            <p>THe word of the Lord to all you Hawkers and Hunters, who are carried up in the fleſh, vapouring, vaunting up your ſelves, ſwelling in your vanities, boiſterous, glorying in your ſtrength, lifted up, exalted, puffed up, lofty and high minded.</p>
            <p>This all is contrary to the way of God, and all ſuch they that dwelt in the life of the Scriptures declared againſt, and all this which is acted out from the nature, which is contrary to the light, is to be condemned with the light, and all that will fade and wither away. Lament, and repent, and turn unto the Lord God, all ye that follow ſuch courſes, actions and practices, while you have time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſau</hi> was a Hunter, he deſpiſed his birth-right, and after fought it with wars, and there was no place of repentance found. To you all Hunters, who are lifted up, who are prophane, as your father <hi>Eſau</hi> was: he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a place for Dragons, and a Wilderneſs, and deſolate, and barren, Dragon is a devourer. Therefore O take heed and be warned.</p>
            <p>Now to that in your conſciences I do ſpeak, which he hath enlightned you withal, it will let you ſee your prophaneſs, your hunting ravening minde, your deſtroying minde, which deſtroys the creature, and deſtroys the creation upon your own luſts, and the whole creation groaneth with that bondage of corruption: nay, you take pleaſure in deſtroying the creatures, and make your ſelves ſport in deſtroying them, running to Alehouſes, drinking healths, and tempting one another with beer, and he that doth not pledge him, doth not love him, and all this love is in the luſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:107633:5"/>
O! woe, woe is your portion, what will become of you in the end? O conſider whither ye muſt go. Remember <hi>Dives,</hi> remember <hi>Eſau</hi> your father, the Hunter, remember <hi>Nimrod</hi> the cunning Hunter, the beginner of the building of <hi>Babel,</hi> whom God confounded into many languages which your teachers tells you, <hi>Is the original;</hi> but he that comes before <hi>Babel</hi> was, comes before many languages was, and before <hi>Nimrod</hi> was.</p>
            <p>Here you and all your languages are raced out; and all ye Hunters which turn from the light which Chriſt hath enlightned you withal, which devours the creation, and you are to be hewen down with the word, which was in the beginning: <hi>In the beginning was the word,</hi> as you may read in <hi>John,</hi> the word was before <hi>Babel</hi> was.</p>
            <p>Therefore to the light in your conſciencess I ſpeak, which Chriſt hath enlightned you withal, that with it you may ſee your filthy mindes and filthineſs, and prophaneſs, and with it all may be judged down, and out: for from God it is judged all, and from them who are of God, and from them who love the light of God, and ſo all prophaneſs and cunning Hunters which are turned from the juſt, which devours the creation upon the luſts, and burthens and grieves the creation, prophane perſons, all you who are prophane, <hi>Eſau</hi> is your father, you cunning Hunters, and not <hi>Jacob,</hi> who was a perfect man, and dwelt in tents, he was not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane; but it was <hi>Eſau</hi> that was prophane, the cunning Hunter, which deſpiſed his birth-right.</p>
            <p>So to you all which turn from the pure in you, the juſt, which chuſe the earth before the pure, you are the <hi>Eſaus,</hi> you are the prophane, you deſpiſe your birth-right.</p>
            <p>To that which is juſt in you all I ſpeak, that with it you may ſee when you mindes go forth, and what they go after, after your dogs, your hounds, your hawks, glorying and taking pleaſure in the creatures, more then in the Creator. You are ſuch as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, and with that in your conſciences, it will let you ſee the judgement from God is upon ſuch things.</p>
            <p>Therefore to the light in your conſciences I ſpeak, that with it your mindes may be guided to God, that you may come to know the right uſe of all creatures, and to be uſed in their place and ſervice, as ſervants, to the glory of God, who has created all things to be uſed in their place, and to praiſe him. <hi>Therefore whatſoever you do, let it be done to the praiſe and glory of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when you ſwear, and curſe, and drink healths, and quarrel, and fight, and are deboiſt, and devours the creation upon your luſts, your ſports, which God has created to be uſed in their place and ſervice to his glory, where will ye appear before the Lord?</p>
            <p>O ye devourers of the creation, fear the Lord God, and turn from all your evil wayes and wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>To that in all your conſciences I ſpeak, that you may all ſee what ye have acted, and do act; there is your teacher to God if ye love it, and your
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107633:5"/>condemnation from God if you hate it. To that in you ſhall I be made manifeſt when your condemnation is come.</p>
            <p>You are them that cumber the ground, prophane perſons, cunning hunters, drunkards and loſty ones, which exerciſe Lordſhip one over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, you are out of the doctrine of Chriſt, you are them that ſtains the earth; but the Lord God of might and power is coming, the ſword of the Almighty is drawn, to hew you down fruitleſs trees, that cumber the ground, and to ſweep and cleanſe the land of evil doers, that the earth may enjoy her Sabbaths.</p>
            <p>All ye that are prophane, are in the nature of <hi>Eſau.</hi> And all you that are proud are in the nature of proud <hi>Haman,</hi> who was out of the truth from God, and you are abomination to the Lord, though you may profeſs Chriſt in words, and yet are workers of iniquity; to you I ſay, Depart from iniquity, that names his Name. And all ye that are ſcoffers, you are of <hi>Iſmael, Iſaac</hi> did not ſcoff, nor <hi>Jacob</hi> was not prophane.</p>
            <p>Therefore to all you that are turned from the light, and are ſcoffers and prophane, you are to be condemned with the light from God, from Chriſt, and all the holy men of God. And to you all this is the word of God.</p>
            <p>And to you all that love the light, walk in the light, that it may lead you from all ſuch actions, contrary to it, up to God the Father of light, and to condemn all that is contrary to the light.</p>
            <p>CUmber not the ground ye fruitleſs trees; ye proud ones, ye ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, cumber not the ground; ye drunkards, ye cumber the ground; ye cumber the ground, ye lyers, cheaters and coze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; ye cumber the ground, who uſe deceit; ye mockers and luſtful ones, which devours the creation, ye are the fruitleſs trees that cumber the ground; you fair outſide profeſſors and teachers, you cumber the ground, who lives in high ſwelling words, but in pride and oppreſſion, and you are the trees that bear leaves, but no fruit; ſo ye are they that cumber the ground.</p>
            <p>The Lord is coming in power to ſweep the land of evil doers, and to hew you down you fruitleſs trees which cumber the ground.</p>
            <p>The fields have been overgrown with thiſtles and nettles, and the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard is ſpoiled for want of dreſſing and labourers; but now the Lord is ſending forth labourers to dreſs the vineyard. A day of howling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you.</p>
            <p>The mountains, and hills, and great ones muſt be threſhed and beaten down, the Lord hath ſpoken it; ſhe hath ſent into his vineyard, to gather fruit, <hi>And every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit must be hewen down and caſt into the fire. A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit, neither can an evil tree bring forth good fruit,</hi> ſuch as the tree is, ſuch is the fruit.</p>
            <p>Drunkard, ſwearer, curſed ſpeaker, thou art this corrupt evil tree, whoremonger, envious one, fighter, quarrellers, malicious ones, ſcorner, mocker, reproacher, thou art this corrupt tree, that cannot bring forth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107633:6"/>good fruit, thou who liveſt in pleaſures and luſtful wayes, lofty and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, thou art this corrupt tree, thou cannot bring forth good fruit; diſſemblers, cheaters, cozeners, thou art this corrupt tree which cannot bring forth good fruit; ſcorner, ſcoffer, who lives in the diſſimulation, and with craft and hypocriſie, thou art the corrupt tree which cannot bring forth good fruit; and all that profeſs God, and Chriſt, and Prophets, and Apoſtles, and lives in ſin and iniquity, you are the curſed tree, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring forth good fruit; for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Depart from me all ye workers of iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All you that pleads for ſin Prieſts and people, are this tree which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring forth good fruit, and pleads for your own maſter, whoſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion you are, and the blood of Chriſt doth but ſerve you to talk of; all you corrupt trees have but boughs, a fair ſhew you make, but when fruit is ſought, there is none found on you, you are they that cumber the ground. The Lord is coming into his vineyard to hew you down, all you luſtful ones, you drunkards, all you railers, and falſe accuſers, all you covetous oppreſſors cumber not the ground.</p>
            <p>The glittering ſword is drawn, it is fourbiſhed for the ſlaughter. The Lords eye is opened, and his hand is ſtretched out againſt his enemies.</p>
            <p>Now woe, woe unto ye wicked, ye have deſpiſed trembling and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tremble, tremble, tremble and quake, O all ye nations; for the whirlwinde is gone forth, that you ſhall be ſcattered as chaff, the day of the Lord is appearing that ſhall burn as an oven, that you ſhall be conſumed as ſtubble: and the trumpet is ſounding out of the holy mountain, that all the inhabitants of the land ſhall tremble; and the Lord is uttering forth his voice before his hoſte; and the day of the Lord is grown very terrible, who can abide it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Drunkard, ſwearer, lyer, thou cannot hide thy ſelf; witchcraft, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers, ſcorners, cheaters, diſſemblers, the Lord will finde you all out; all your pretence of God and Chriſt, ſhall ſtink heavy in your faces, you diſſemblers, for God will not be mocked with words; wo and miſery, a day of howling amongſt you lofty ones, a day of howling among you luſtful ones, your throates will be be drie, parched; and woe is thy portion, thou luſtful one, thy luſt ſhall not be fed, who hath devoured the whole crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. A day of howling amongſt you covetous oppreſſours, taksmaſter, who hath devoured the creation, and doth devour it: ſome creatures are deſtroyed for want of ordering, and upon your luſts; ſome creatures are deſtroyed for want of creatures.</p>
            <p>You are them that cumber the ground, and the Lord is coming with his whirlwinde to ſweep you away, and the earth ſhall yield her increaſe, and come to enjoy her Sabbaths, and the righteous ſhall inherit it, and the land ſhall be cleanſed of evil doers, <hi>Sion</hi> is threſhing, and a fan is come to fan, and the Lord is at work in his vineyard, and the arrows of of the Almighty are ſhooting forth againſt the wicked, and hell hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened her mouth to receive all you workers of iniquity, and hell gapes for you.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:107633:6"/>
Tremble and be aſtoniſhed you heathen that knows not God; for you are all heathens that know not God, and the land is full of crooked waies, the land is full of rough places, the land is full of hills and mountains, the land is full of bryers and thorns, dogs and ſwine, fighting and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſnarling and biting one another, for the husks, and for the earthly creatures.</p>
            <p>Therefore all people repent, repent while you have time; for the mighty day of the Lord is coming<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore hearken to that which ſhews you ſin and evil, there is your teacher loving it, there is your condemnation ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it.</p>
            <p>THe word of the Lord to all ye fruitleſs trees, ye dry trees, ye oaks, ye tall cedars, ye fat bulls of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> ye thorns, ye briers, ye wilde aſſes which ſnuſt up your noſes in the top of the mountains &amp; the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, ye high-way-ground, ye ſtony-ground, ye goats, ye wolves, ye dogs, ye ſwine, ye ſerpents, ye vulterous ones, ye beaſts, ye lyons, ye ſtrong horſes neighing up and down, walking after your luſts: this is not railing, this is the Scripture-language. Own your names every one in your place, with the light ye are all ſeen, and your names comes to be known; ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one bears, your name according to your nature; ye are them that cumber the ground, ye are them that are not of the light, ye are them that are to be condemned with the light; ye that are unjuſt ye cumber the ground. Woe unto you drunkards, ye cumber the ground; woe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you hypocrites, ye cumber the ground; woe unto you lyers, ye cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the ground; woe unto you ſcoffers, ye cumber the ground; ſcorners and backbiters, ye cumber the ground; diſſemblers, ye are them that cumber the ground; the hand of the Lord is againſt you.</p>
            <p>To that in your conſciences I ſpeak, which ſhall witneſs me eternally; ye drunkards ye cumber the ground; ye rotten hearts, ye falſe-hearts, and diſſemblers, ye cumber the ground, ye oppreſs the creation, the land mourns becauſe of ſuch; ye devourers, ye murtherers, ye are they that pollutes the earth, ye cumber the ground.</p>
            <p>Fear, fear the Lord God, tremble before him, ye that make a profeſſion of Chriſt and God, and live in deceit, ye are lyers ye cumber the ground, ye are of the devil, ye abide not in the truth; for you do not abide in the life that gave forth the Scripture; ſo you are not what you profeſs, in life and power; but hath the words, the form, and makes a trade of them.</p>
            <p>Woe unto you devourers, that devour the people, and make a prey of them; ye luſtful ones which follows pleaſure, rioting, feaſting, ſporting, drunkenneſs, guttony, hawking, hunting, <hi>Elau</hi>-like, ye cumber the ground, ye are the place for the dragon, ye are as the wilderneſs, fruitleſs. And to you this is the word of God.</p>
            <p>To that in your conſciences I ſpeak, as you love it, it will ariſe in you, and you will ſee your ſelves, and ſee the Scriptures, ye ungodly ones, ye
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107633:7"/>covetous walk after your ungodly luſts; ye vain talkers, ye cumber the ground; ye are as the caterpillers, ye are as the locuſts that go without a King, which are turned from the light; ye are for the ſword to be ſlain; ye which mindes earthly things, whoſe mindes are turned from the light, which walk after your own ungodly luſts, ye defile the fleſh, ye cumber the ground; ye careleſs ones, the hand of the Lord is againſt you, ye which follow fooliſh boaſting, fooliſh talking, fooliſh ſongs, and ſpends your time in ſuch wayes.</p>
            <p>O woe and miſery is coming upon you! how do you ſpend your time? and how have you loſt your time? hell gapes and opens her mouth to receive you, where all the wicked are turned into. Stand ſtill a while and ſee whither all ye muſt go.</p>
            <p>To the light in you I ſpeak, that with it ye may ſee your ſelves, &amp; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber your ſelves, and with it you may ſee, no unrighteouſneſs muſt enter the kingdom of God, and this which ſhews you it, is the light of Chriſt within you; and loving it, it will lead you from all ſuch actions and practices as are contrary to it; and with it all ſuch things are to be condemned.</p>
            <p>This is your teacher the light; this is it will bring you to witneſs Chriſt, who is the way to the Father; and this is it that will bring you to yea and nay in all your communications; and this will teach you good manners, to deny all evill communication; and this will bring you to lay aſide all deceitful merchandiſe, all luſts, pleaſures, filthy practices, which the world lives in; and this is it which is pure, and teaches pureneſs and holineſs, without which none ſhall ever ſee God.</p>
            <p>You that are proud and lofty, cumbers the ground; ye are abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Lord God, with the light you are ſeen, with the light you are comprehended, with the light you are judged. To the light in you I ſpeak, which will let you ſee vainity, one vanity upon another</p>
            <p>To the light in all your conſciences I ſpeak everywhere, which will let you ſee all that is contrary to it. To that I am made manifeſt, the light, which if you love it, it will guide your hearts together into unity; for the unity is in the light, and up to God the Father of light, and there is your teacher preſent alwaies whitherſoever ye go, or lying in your bed, this light doth not change, to which I ſpeak, thou that changeth, acts contrary to it, and with this light which changeth not, art to be condemned from God who changeth not, and to be the itching ears, and in the doctrine of the devil, and amongſt the fables.</p>
            <p>THe word of the Lord to you all, who are turned from the light which Jeſus Chriſt hath enlightned you withal, &amp; do hate it, who follows pleaſures, who are ſuch as the Scriptures ſpeaks of, who are ſporting your ſelves in the day time, living in wantonneſs; you are ſuch as the Scripture ſpeaks of, which the Apoſtle that dwelled in the light cried againſt, ſpoke againſt and judged; you are ſcoffers and ſcorners glorying in your ſtrength; ye are ſuch as the Scripture ſpeaks of, which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107633:7"/>were ever judged with the life that gave forth the Scriptures, and are to be condemned with the light. You that follow drunkenneſs, fighting and adultery, and idolatry, pride and envie, you are ſuch as defiles the fleſh, you are ſuch that the Scripture ſpeaks of, that were judged with the life that gave it forth, and which it ever declared againſt. You that follow bowls, and cards, and ſhovelboord, and drinking healths, and have muſick, the Harp, the Viol, the Lute; ye are ſuch as the Lord ſent <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to cry againſt, and you act contrary to the light, and you are in the works of the fleſh, in that nature out of the light; and with the light you are to be condemned, and all your works are for the fire, who caſts the law of God behind your backs, which is perfect according to the light in your conſciences, which judges down all that which is not perfect, with the light all thoſe actions are ſeen, which are in that nature contrary to the light; ſo with the light all ſuch are condemned from God.</p>
            <p>You that follow foot-bal-playing, cudgel-playing, fencing, exerciſing your ſelves at back-ſwords or rapiers, you are glorying in your ſtrength, ye are boaſting, ye are vapouring, ye are diſdaming, ye are deſpiſing, you are envying, you are in pride, you are in ambition, with the light which Chriſt: hath enlightned you withal, you are to be condemned from God, and all theſe practiſes I ſee them all, that manhood, and all that fame, and all that renown, it muſt be laid down in the duſt.</p>
            <p>And you that follow wreſtlings, and leapings, and dancings, you are ſuch that live in the fleſh without the fear of God, you are inventing with that minde which goes from the light, and with the light you are to be condemned from God, who lives in the luſts of the fleſh, and theſe actions of the fleſh.</p>
            <p>And ye that delight in ſongs, in tunes, and jeſting books, and ballads, rhimes, themes, inventing verſes, you are in the fables, you are ſuch as the Scriptures ſpeaks of, acting in that nature which is out of the truth, which with the light, all ſuch works of the fleſh are to be condemned; this will wither, this will fade away and paſs away.</p>
            <p>And all you that follow horſe-racing, you are in the boaſting, you are idolaters, and adulterers, and you are covetous, you are they that oppoſe the creation, you are chalenging and envying when you cannot get your will, and when you have your will, this is in <hi>Cain</hi>'s way, which is for condemnation, who walks in the way which is ungodly.</p>
            <p>Ye that follow merchandize, buyes and ſells, and makes a trade of it, and buy the creature at one towne, and ſells them at another market; <hi>It's naught, it's naught,</hi> you ſay, when you come to buy, and, <hi>They are bad, they are bad:</hi> and when you have bought them, then, <hi>They are the beſt in the market,</hi> and then you ſet up that which you ſaid was nought. So with the light which ſhews your lying, your deceit, your falſe-hearts, are you with it to be condemned, who lives in theſe cuſtomes of ſin, which hath taken away the ſence, you are in the thieviſh nature that do ſo, that buy and ſell the creatures to oppreſs them, and ſay it is naught for your own ends, and then ſay it is good for your own ends.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:107633:8"/>
To the light in all your conſciences I ſpeak, which will witneſs me, and will let you ſee what diſſemblers you are, and how far you are out of the doctrine of Chriſt, which is yea and nay in all communication; who when you come to cheap a thing or buy a thing, you ſay, <hi>You will give no more for it, not a peny;</hi> and the ſeller ſaith likewiſe the ſame, he ſaith, <hi>No, be will not take a penny leſs,</hi> then they preſently yeild one to another, out of the yea and nay to be, and with the light which bring to yea and nay to be condemned, to it I ſpeak, and it ſhall witneſs me againſt all the deceits of the world, and all deceitful merchandiſe, who act without the fear of God.</p>
            <p>And all you that follow feaſtings and weddings, your Prieſts acted in that nature out of the light, with the light is to be condemned; yet mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is honourable in all, where the bed is not defiled.</p>
            <p>And you that turn from the light, which invent pictures, idols, and ſet them up, you are in the nature turned from the light; ye and all your images is to be condemned, and ye that are turned from the light of Chriſt, which is eternal, that minde invents croſſes, forms a croſs, imitates a croſs, which dwelling in the light it ſelf, is a croſs to the ground, which forms theſe croſſes; and to you this is the word of God.</p>
            <p>And ſo, here both the image, and the image-maker, and the founder of the image, dwelling in this croſs muſt be deſtroyed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="description_of_manners">
            <head>Good and bad manners diſtinguiſhed.</head>
            <p>COrrupt communications corrupts the good manners. Now if you love the light which Chriſt hath enlightned you withal, it will bring you to yea and nay in all your communications; for whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is more, is evil. And you that turn from this light which Chriſt hath enlightned you withal, then in your communications ye are not yea and nay; and ſo you are in the evil, and out of the doctrine of Chriſt; and ſo in that nature you may be taught to bend, to bow, to cringe one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, with cap and knee, and hand and foot, (and ſo calls that civil and and good manners, and he that doth not, with ſuch is judged not to be not civil, who lives in the pure communication yea and nay, and can bow to none but the Lord,) yet full of envie and pride, and where there is pride, there is envie, and wrath, and rage, and ſury, <hi>Cain</hi>-like in your commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications, ſome are mocking, ſome ſtriking, and ſome are railing to the face, and backbiting, and yet when they meet, they flatter one another with the cap, and ſtrake with the foot, and bow with the hand and knee, and yet full of envie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:107633:8"/>
To the light of Chriſt in your conſciences I ſpeak, which if you love it, it will bring you to bow to the Lord, and let you ſee theſe things, and bring you to yea and nay in all your communications, and then nothing ſhall reign but Chriſt Jeſus; for the light will condemn all things which is contrary to it, and which hath been bowed down to, which is contrary to the light, and that which would reſpect the perſons of men, comes to be judged; for it is the trangreſſor of that which is pure, tranſgreſſeth the pure law of God, and with the pure that comes to be judged, and if you love the light of Chriſt which he hath enlightned you withal, it will bring you to put away all vain communications out of your mouthes, and keep you to yea and nay in all communications, and it will teach you the good manners; for all you who live in your vain communications from yea and nay, all your profeſſion, which the Prophets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles hath ſpoken, you having their words and the form, and gone from yea and nay, out of the doctrine of Chriſt, with the life of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and the light of Chriſt, you are to be condemned, and the end of your profeſſion is wo, as Chriſt ſaid to the Scribes and Phariſees.</p>
            <p>So you that are turned from the pure light of Chriſt within you, you are in your vain communicaitons, and do worſhip the beaſt; for that which turneth from the light of Chriſt, it ſets up that which is out of the truth which is the beaſt, ſo the plagues of God proceeds upon who are all turned from the light of Chriſt, ſuch are in the vain commuications and corrupt manners, and are to be condemned.</p>
            <p>But to you all that love the light of Chriſt, and your mindes guided by it, it will teach you the pure and good manners, and all the corrupt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners will be judged and condemned with the light which Chriſt hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned you withal, which light will teach you to walk with God and men, and there is all your teacher, loving it; and there is all your condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, hating it.</p>
            <p>You that live in filthineis, pride, in luſt, in curſed ſpeaking, in wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſporting your ſelves in the day-time, and fooliſh jeſting, and drunkenneſs, and gluttony, and all the corruption that are in that nature which is turned from the light, are in the evil communication, and the corrupt manners which is to be condemned with the light, which light e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one in particular loving it, which Chriſt hath enlightned every one withal, it will teach you and bring to yea and nay in all your communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and it will teach you the good manners.</p>
            <p>It is the eye which will let you ſee Chriſt the head, and there is your teacher the light which Chriſt hath enlightned every one of you withal in particular, which will let you ſee your evil deeds, and when you act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it, which if you hate it, it will be your condemnation.</p>
            <p>To the light of Chriſt in every one of your conſciences I ſpeak, which will witneſs me when the book of conſcience is opened, which light will teach you at all times, walking up and down, &amp; lying in bed, in all your actions; this light will teach you when you are in your merchandiſe, if you do not juſtly the light will let you ſee it, it will check you and ſecretly condemn
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107633:9"/>you; that is the light which ſhews you your evil deed; which if you love it, it will keep you to yea and nay in all your communications, it will bring you to few words, and bring you into the fear of the Lord, and <hi>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is to be ſet upon all Croſſes, that all may ſee the good manners, and the corrupt manners, and the corrupt communication, which corrupts the good manners, and the pure communication which is yea and nay, according to the light of Chriſt in every one of your conſciences. To the light of Chriſt in every one of your conſciences I do ſpeak.</p>
            <p>From them whom the world calls Quakers ſcornfully; but <hi>Moſes</hi> who quaked and trembled, ſaid, <hi>To him reproaches was great riches.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
